Finding Aid for Willard Clifford Olson papers, 1920-1973
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Willard Clifford Olson papers 1920-1973
Olson, Willard Clifford, 1899-1978.
85331 Aa 2
Professor of education and psychology at the University of Michigan, director of child development research, 1929-1952, and dean of the University's School of Education, 1952-1970. Professional correspondence and topical files concerning his interest in the University's elementary school, the Interamerican Society of Psychology, and UNESCO; reprints and manuscripts of writings; speeches relating to education, child development and child psychology; and visual materials.
6.2 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mrs. Willard C. Olson (donor no. 4039 ) in 1979. The videocassette came from Mrs. Mary Anne Hayes (donor no. 6907 ) in 1983. A portion of the collection came as part of the records of the U-M School of Education (donor no. 1220 ) and came to the library in 1986.
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The collection is open to research.
Willard Clifford Olson was born October 8, 1899 in Annadale, Minnesota. He graduated from the University of Minnesota (A.B., 1920; A.M., 1924; and Ph.D., 1926). He was an instructor at the University of Minnesota, 1923-1926, and then, after receiving his doctorate, an assistant professor of educational psychology, 1927-1929.
He came to the University of Michigan in 1929, serving as director of research in child development, which position he held until 1952. He also received appointment as associate professor of education (1929-1935), then promoted to full professor in 1935. In 1946, Olson was also appointed professor of psychology. In 1952, he became dean of the School of Education, serving until 1970. He died October 30, 1978.
Professor Olson was a noted expert in the field of child development and educational psychology. He was a member of various professional organizations. He also wrote numerous articles in the field, notably Child Development (1949; rev. 1959).
The Willard C. Olson collection consists of professional correspondence and topical files concerning his interest in the University's elementary school, the Interamerican Society of Psychology, and UNESCO; reprints and manuscripts of writings; speeches relating to education, child development and child psychology; and visual materials. The collection is organized into the following series: Personal/Biographical; Correspondence; Manuscripts, articles, reviews, and speeches; Topical files; Miscellaneous; Visual Materials; and Topical Files transferred from the U-M School of Education record group in 1995.
Subjects:
Olson, Willard Clifford, 1899-1978.; Child development.; Child psychology.; Education.; Interamerican Society of Psychology.; Psychology.; UNESCO.; University Elementary School (Ann Arbor, Mich.); University of Michigan. Dept. of Psychology.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. School of Education.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Children.; Olson, Willard Clifford, 1899-1978.; Olson family.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Videotapes.
- Personal/Biographical
  - Personal data (Box 1)
  - Bibliography of WCO's publications (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings, 2 folders (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - By date
    - Undated 1920-1971, 18 folders (Box 1)
  - By name
    - Elkisch, Paula Brunn 1941-1956 (Box 1)
    - Fuller, Elizabeth Mechem 1941, 1950-1961 (Box 1)
    - UNESCO 1952-1968, 4 folders (Box 1)
- Manuscripts, articles, reviews, and speeches
  - The Constancy and Reliability of an Intelligence Quotient Determined by the Haggerty Intelligence Examination Delta 2, 1924 (Box 1)
  - The Measurement and Incidence of Behavior Problems and Problem Tendencies in Children, 1926 (Box 1)
  - Neurotic Tendencies in Children: Criteria, Incidence and Differential Tests, 1927 (Box 1)
    (Final report as Fellow of the National Research Council Board of Fellowships in the Biological Sciences)
  - A Personnel Study of Students in the College of Education of the University of Minnesota, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Reprints and manuscripts (arranged alphabetically), 7 folders (Box 2)
  - Reviews of WCO's publications (Box 3)
  - Reviews by WCO, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Speeches
    - Alphabetical series, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Radio talks (Box 3)
    - Lecture notes re "Children who surprised us" (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous lecture and speech material, 3 folders (Box 3)
- Topical files 1938-1972
  - Ad hoc Committee on the Shortage of Teachers in Michigan (report) September 1956 (Box 3)
  - American Psychological Association
    - Papers 1960-1973 (Box 3)
    - Historical Summary, 1892-1930 and proceedings 1938-1945 (Box 3)
  - Committee on International Relations of Psychology 1956-1960, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Archives of the History of American Psychology, University of Akron 1966-1968 (Box 3)
  - British Psychological Society 1943-1972 (Box 3)
  - Case illustrations (Box 3)
  - Child Development (relating to his book)
    - Materials and correspondence, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - German translation (Box 3)
  - Child growth patterns (Box 3)
  - Child psychology in dentistry for children (Box 3)
  - Cooperative studies for the better utilization of teacher competencies, Central Michigan College 1953-1956 (Box 4)
  - Educational research organization 1957 (Box 4)
  - Growth ages, Intercorrelations (Box 4)
  - Haggerty-Olson-Wickman behavior rating schedules 1929-1934, 1970 (Box 4)
  - Interamerican Society of Psychology
    - 1953 (Box 4)
    - 1954 (Box 4)
    - 1955 (Box 4)
    - 1956-1960 (Box 4)
    - 1961-1962 (Box 4)
    - 1963-1966 (Box 4)
    - News bulletins 1959-1971 (miscellaneous issues) (Box 4)
  - Michigan Ad Hoc Committee on the Shortage of Teachers 1956 (Box 4)
  - United States Office of Education, Cooperative Research Program 1955-1958, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - University of Michigan
    - School of Education papers (Box 4)
    - University Elementary School
      - Papers (Box 4)
      - Child development laboratories
        - Papers (Box 4)
        - Bibliography (Box 4)
    - University High School, Adolescent research project, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - University of Michigan Extension Service telecourse, "Understanding the Child," 1951-1952 (Box 4)
- Miscellaneous
  - Miscellaneous graphs and charts (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous bibliographies (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous articles relating to child development and/or psychology, 3 folders (Box 4)
- Visual materials
  - Photographs (Box 5)
  - Videocassette, "Understanding the Child", parts 1 and 3, 2 videotapes U-matic (Box 5)
    (program features Olson's grandchildren)
- Topical Files 1929-1952
  (Files transferred from the U-M School of Education record group in 1995/)
  - American Orthopsychiatric Association 1930-1936 (Box 6)
  - American Psychological Association
    - General 1929-1951, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Committee on Publications 1934 (Box 6)
    - Committee reports 1926-1927 (Box 6)
  - Ann Arbor Pre-School Play Groups circa 1940 (Box 6)
  - Army Leadership Scale 1942-1944 (Box 6)
  - Boys Clubs of America 1941-1944 (Box 6)
  - Cambridge-Somerville Youth Study 1937-1939 (Box 6)
  - Children's Fund of Michigan 1929-1951 (Box 6)
  - Citizenship Education Survey (Detroit) 1945-1946 (Box 6)
  - Cooperative Study, Six Experimental Schools-Columbia University 1938-1949 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence 1939-1951 (A-E only) (Box 6)
  - Correspondence with Dean James B. Edmonson 1929-1952, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Correspondence with faculty 1934-1950 (A-Z), 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Course materials
    - Education B-191 & B-192 (education research methods), 3 folders (Box 6)
    - Education C-375a (Seminar in Human Development) (Box 6)
  - Improvement of Human Relations case study circa 1940 (Box 6)
  - Kellogg (W.K.) Foundation Camps
    - General 1937-1938 (Box 6)
    - Michigan Community Health Projects Camps 1936-1937, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Olson, Willard
    - Photograph portrait (Box 7)
    - Papers
      - "Child Development for Teachers" (Box 7)
      - "Neurotic Tendencies in Children" 1927 (Box 7)
      - "The Prediction of Mental and Social Maladjustment" (preface only) (Box 7)
      - "The Prediction of Delinquency from Early Behavior" circa 1937, 4 folders (Box 7)
    - Student papers circa 1919 (Box 7)
  - Summer Sessions course materials 1937-1941, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - University Elementary School
    - Miscellaneous (Box 7)
    - Conception and construction 1929-1930, 3 folders (Box 7)
    - Curriculum Committee 1932 (Box 7)
    - Program/curriculum meetings 1937-1941 (Box 7)
    - Adolescence Research Program 1951 (Box 7)
    - Psychometric Unit
      - Annual reports 1931-1954 (Box 7)
      - Manual of Practice (Box 7)